What if I told you in this video I'm
going to teach you the holy grail
trading strategy. A foolproof series of
steps, rules, and criteria that you just
need to learn and follow to become
consistently profitable for the rest of
your life. Well, you would obviously
think that I'm full of [__] and rightly
so. Great instinct. But luckily, that's
not what I'm going to teach you in this
video. You see, every trader who's been
doing this for more than a month or has
more than two brain cells in their head
knows that there's no such thing as a
holy grail trading strategy. You might
hope there is, but deep down, you know
it doesn't exist. There's no perfect
sequence you can follow each and every
time to consistently succeed in the
markets over a large sample size. You
might have a lucky week. You might even
have a lucky month. You're not going to
have a lucky career. But that doesn't
stop people pushing the idea on social
media. They might not call it a holy
grail strategy, but their simple
five-step strategy that prints me 10K a
month or simple trick that increased my
trade success rate 75%
suggests otherwise. You see, people
online always try to dumb down trading
to the most basic steps because
simplicity sells. But since you're
watching this video, I'm guessing you're
not buying that. But what if I told you
there's a good chance you're actually
doing something very similar without
even realizing it and it's probably
holding you back from achieving the sort
of performance that you know that you're
capable of. That's what I'm going to
explain in this video. I'm going to help
you to understand the problem to know
why it happens to see how it negatively
impacts your trading performance and how
to solve it. and I'll walk you through a
simple, yes, the irony is not lost on me
on that one, practical exercise that you
can do today to start figuring out clear
areas of improvement. See how this
problem is appearing in your trading and
how to cut it the [__] out. And as
always, if you want more of my insights
and lessons from over 20 years in the
markets and breakdowns of some of my
trades, you can sign up for free using
the link in the description box. And
you'll get all the training that I don't
share on the YouTube channel and that
you won't find being taught anywhere
else. All at no cost. So even if you're
just curious, you got nothing to lose.
You might as well sign up. All right.
Always worth a try. So let's get started
by reflecting on where things stand for
you right now. I want to ask you some
questions and please take some time to
think through your answer. Pause the
video if you have to. So, when you sit
down to improve your trading, what do
you actually work on? What is it that
you're doing when you're trying to
improve your trading? Or when you hit a
period of bad performance, what do you
actually try to change to get things
back on track? And if there was one
improvement that could make you
consistently profitable, what do you
think that improvement is going to be?
Now, be honest. Don't think about what
sounds like the right answer, but think
about what you actually do. How are you
spending your time right now? Don't
cheat yourself with this one. Because
here's the interesting part. When most
traders answer those questions honestly,
what they describe usually isn't skill
development. It's not skill improvement.
It's about their system, their strategy.
It's about adjusting things in their
strategy in some way. changing their
rules, changing their entry or exit
criteria, the way they apply different
levels or indicators, the parameters, or
getting better at following the rules
and figuring out ways to get themselves
to actually stick to them properly. You
know, people say, "If I just stuck to my
system, if I stuck to my strategy, I'd
be succeeding. I know what I'm meant to
be doing and I can't get myself to do
it." So, they try and box themselves in
to be able to do that. And I see it
constantly in emails that I receive from
traders. They'll say things like they
hit a rough patch, then they tweaked
their strategy and now things magically
seem to be getting better. They stopped
trading reversals and switched to just
trading breakouts. They moved to a
different time frame. They changed
markets, started scaling in or only now
trade with the trend. All these
different things. And magically now
things seems to be working. But what
that really says is the rules are what's
going to make me profitable or it's the
rules that make me profitable. Just find
the right combination, stick to it,
problem solved. In other words, you
don't think you believe in a holy grail
trading strategy. But if you're
completely honest, your actions suggest
otherwise. Your actions suggest that
you're still working towards one. It's
the holy grail mindset just disguised as
something a bit more sophisticated. So
the important question, why does this
happen? Well, I think there are three
clear reasons. Now, I'm sure there are
many other reasons, but these are the
three most common ones I believe.
Firstly, the trading education industry
has brainwashed everyone to believe that
success in trading comes from finding
the right strategy and then learning to
stick with it. But it doesn't. Success
in trading comes from developing the
right skills. But this then relates to
the second reason. Most traders,
including the so-called gurus, don't
even know what skills they should be
developing. They're usually not even
aware of the skills that matter the
most. So, if they know that their
trading performance is down here,
they're doing badly, they're losing
money, and they want to bring it all the
way up to here where they can start
profiting from their trading, well, they
know they've got to work on something to
bridge that gap. It's not going to
happen by itself. But if you don't know
what skills you actually need to be
developing to reach that point, instead
you'll look for something else that
feels tangible to work on, which is
often rules. It feels productive, but
really it's just like rearranging the
deck chairs on the Titanic. You're not
dealing with the core problem. If you
want to know what skills you need to
develop, how to track them, how to
improve them over time, and learn a
logical approach to trading, then just
sign up using the link in the
description box that I mentioned
earlier. Now, the third reason is that
your brain loves order. There's a
concept in psychology known as
compensatory control theory. And it
explains our need as humans to have a
sense of structure and predictability in
the world around us. And because of
that, when things are particularly
chaotic or out of our control in
particular situations, we'll cling on to
order and structure that we can control
more than we usually would. And this is
why you see like sports people following
weird rituals and superstitions to keep
themselves grounded. And it's why
traders feel more comfortable following
rules. Because here's the thing, none of
us, not us here, not me presenting this
video to you, not you watching it, can
control the markets. And things don't
always follow an orderly structure. But
by creating our own structure and our
own rules, we create a sense of order
that provides us with comfort. It feels
systematic, measurable, and safe. But
it's an illusion because the truth is
mechanical rules trading rarely ever
works over a large sample size. It's
popular online because it's easy to sell
and it's easy to learn. It's easy to
explain. It's easy to follow. When A and
B happens, C is likely to happen next.
So enter a trade at that point. But the
thing is markets are adaptive and
dynamic. Activity levels change, drivers
in the market change, behavior changes,
context changes. Just like we talked
about in the last video, there are
endless ways that context can appear in
the markets and it's different each and
every time. Of course, there are
sometimes similarities, but there are
also a lot of differences and the
differences matter. No fixed set of
conditions is going to accurately
capture that. And yes, I hear it all the
time. Yeah, but quant traders use
mechanical systems and they're among the
most successful traders in the markets.
Well, no, not like retail traders try to
do. Real quant systems encode adaptable
logic and probabilistic context. And
that's why banks hire PhDs as quants and
don't just buy a 50 quid EA from Tik Tok
shop. Give me a [__] break. But
listen, jokes aside, it's not just fully
mechanical systems that I'm talking
about here. So, I don't want you sitting
there thinking, well, I don't use
mechanical rules trading, so this
doesn't apply to me. Because it probably
does. It's rules in general that I'm
talking about. Even within my own
community, I see it. So at Duomo, our
approach is about analyzing the markets
to understand the unique context of that
specific moment, forecasting the
potential price moves, what we call
potential outcomes, accurately
estimating the probabilities of them
based on the context and our
understanding of the markets, and then
executing trades when those outcomes
show positive expectancy. Now, that
relies on developing the necessary
skills. No set of rules is going to do
that for you. And I sometimes see
comments where people complain that this
approach means there's too much
discretion. Um yeah, like what do you
expect? It's a set of skills. We're
talking about forecasting the global
financial markets, not speed running a
video game. But here's the thing. Even
though our members know all of that,
they understand why it's important to
approach the markets that way and how
effective it can be. You'll still see
members trying to fit what they see in
the markets, the context, into these
tidy boxes of predetermined conditions
that they can then rely upon. You love
your boxes. That way, they just have to
figure out which box to categorize
different things in. And it makes it all
feel very black and white, very
straightforward, rather than having to
make real judgments in the markets,
which then falls into more of a gray
area. But the reality is in the markets,
every trade you take, if you want to
succeed, is going to involve judgment.
And judgment is a skill, not a rule
book. When you rely purely on rules, you
remove that judgment. You're trying to
turn uncertainty into a fixed pattern.
As if A and B happen, then C must follow
on. But the markets don't obey your if
then statements. Now, let me make
something really, really clear because
I'm sure it's going to get
misinterpreted by people. I'm not saying
that rules themselves are useless. I use
rules in my trading as well. Rules can
be incredibly useful. But you need to
understand them for what they really
are. Rules are shortcuts for applying
logic. They're summaries of reasoning,
not replacements for it. So, let me
explain what I mean. So, take any rule
or concept that you currently use in
your trading. Maybe it's that you only
trade in alignment with the higher time
frame trend, the bigger picture trend.
Or maybe you only enter when a
particular type of level has been tested
or broken. Now, when those conditions
are met in the market, is there
something magical happening? Of course
not. Let's be [__] real. Do you think
it's because everyone else is following
the same rule? Now, a lot of traders do
think that's the case, the so-called
self-fulfilling prophecy, but in
99.9999%
of cases, that's simply not true either.
So, those rules, the things that you're
following, are not truths about the
market. They're simplified ways of
applying a particular logic. But if you
follow those rules blindly without
understanding what that logic is or why
the rule exists, you'll miss the deeper
reasoning that actually makes the rule
useful in the first place. Or you'll
fail to see when the rule that you're
following is completely [__]
pointless. And that's why the same rules
that seem to work in one situation lead
to poor performance in almost every
other situation because the context has
changed, but the rule hasn't. and the
logic that's behind that rule doesn't
fit the situation anymore. But if you do
understand the logic behind your rules,
you can adapt to any situation. And if
you don't, you're going to stay trapped
in an endless cycle of trial and error
like most mechanical traders, constantly
tweaking their system because they're
just trying to fix symptoms rather than
actually identifying the root cause and
fixing that because they've never even
diagnosed it. And trust me, I've been
there for many years. Early in my
career, I took everything at face value.
I learned what I was taught and just
tried to stick to it as closely as
possible without ever really asking why.
But that one word, why is probably the
most important one in trading because
when you start to think logically, the
rules stop being the point. You start to
see why things work when they do, why
they fail when they don't, and how
[clears throat] to adapt in those
situations. So, [snorts] deep breath,
rant over. So, I'm going to walk you
through an important practical exercise
that will help you to start fixing this
problem. And I'd really recommend that
you spend a good amount of time doing
this and give it your 100% focus. Don't
think, I'll just do it another time.
Don't skim over it or give it 5 minutes.
Do it properly. Commit to this. So, open
a new document on your computer or grab
a pen and paper if you want. You know,
I'm not your [__] dad. Do what you
want. What I want you to do is to write
down every single element of your
trading approach. every level, every
concept, indicator, technique, pattern,
process, every rule. And don't just stop
at analysis. Also include your strategy
rules, trade management, risk
management, everything that makes up
your trading approach. Now, for each
one, you're going to explain the full
logic behind it, okay? In full. Now, a
good way to do this if you're not sure
how to get started is to follow
something that's similar to the five W's
technique. So start with the rule or
concept and then ask yourself why you
follow it. Why do you adhere to that
rule and when you have your answer, ask
why again and keep going and keep going.
Don't just stop at the surface. Keep
asking why until you can't go any
further. And this should lead you to an
underlying principle if one exists. So
for example, you might say, I plot XY Z
levels and look to enter when price
fails there. Why? because price is more
likely to reverse there. Why? Because
that's where the market does dot dot
dot. Why does that matter? Because it
represents blah blah blah and so on and
so on. You keep going down like that.
Then when you're done and you can't dig
any further for that particular thing,
finish with these three key questions
one, is there evidence of that? So
you've made a claim about the logic of
that particular thing, but can you
actually prove it in some way? Prove
that it's true. Otherwise, how do you
know that it's a fact? Traders claim all
kinds of things about the techniques
that they use, but the simple fact is
that when you objectively test it, the
logic turns out to be complete [__]
It just sounds legit, but it's
completely invented. The second question
is, does the rule capture the full
logic? So, assuming there is evidence
and the logic makes sense, does that
particular rule fully capture it or are
you limiting yourself in some way? You
know, sometimes you'll find that the
rule is actually disconnected from the
true logic or doesn't cover everything
correctly and needs to be changed in
some way. And finally, the third
question is the rule even necessary? So
maybe if you figure out the underlying
logic, you'll find that you can just
apply that logic in each situation
without even needing the rule at all.
And at that point, that's when you start
relying on skill a lot more because
you're able to make appropriate
judgments in each situation rather than
this if then type statement, this binary
approach of following rules or not
following rules. Now, if you do this
exercise properly, you will uncover real
truths about your trading. You'll either
confirm a genuine trading or market
principle, expose something that's
completely baseless, or find gaps in
your understanding that you can finally
fix. Whatever the outcome, you'll
improve by removing what's pointless,
refining what's useful, and developing
the skill to start thinking for
yourself. But listen, the most important
thing here is that you've got to be
honest with yourself. Because it can be
hard to admit that something you've
invested time, effort, and money into
might actually be wrong. That you've
been misled for all of this time. And
that's why most traders end up ignoring
the evidence that's right in front of
them or try to justify it to themselves
despite everything showing they're
wrong. It's a typical case of cognitive
dissonance. I mean, at the end of the
day, you want your trading to be
grounded in logic and not just habits
that you've picked up over time without
questioning them. And once you
understand the logic behind everything
you do, rules start to become more
optional. You know when to bend them or
break them, when to apply them and don't
apply them without losing coherence. And
that's the important thing about a skill
is knowing when you can do certain
things without it being forced, without
it being illogical, where it still makes
sense. it's still coherent. Also, it's
obviously very common to introduce rules
to deal with problems that keep coming
up like certain mistakes you keep making
or problem areas you've seen frequently
in your trading where it's like, okay, I
keep doing this thing wrong, so I'm
going to set a rule so that I don't do
it anymore. Like having a rule where you
stop trading after a certain number of
losses because you keep revenge trading.
But the thing with these sorts of rules
is that they're usually just treating
symptoms and not very well. Most of the
time, you're much better off trying to
dig in to find the root cause behind
that problem and then set an action plan
that works on fixing that specific
thing. That's going to make your trading
so much more stable. But, you know,
research shows that it's the way our
brains work to try and solve problems by
adding things rather than subtracting.
Most of the time, we don't even see the
solutions that involve removing
something, even if it's right in front
of our eyes. But this practical
exercise, if you do it, should help you
to achieve exactly that. So make the
commitment, take the time, and do it
properly. You know, trading isn't about
memorizing the right checklist. It isn't
just a pattern recognition activity,
even though most people treat it that
way. If it was, my 5-year-old nephews
could do it. Instead, it's mostly a
problem-solving activity. It's about
understanding and interpreting the
unique context of each market situation
and using that understanding and
interpretation to make logical decisions
within the right sort of framework. Most
traders blame psychology for their
struggles and why they're failing. But
the real problem most of the time is a
lack of meaningful skill and logic. More
traders would succeed if they change the
way they think about trading. And if
you're currently struggling to see
progress, watch the video that's on
screen now and it will show you the
mindset shifts that will finally put you
on the right path.